Guide to the Amos Alonzo Stagg Papers 1866-1964
University of Chicago Library
- Series VIII: Scrapbooks, Notebooks, and Albums
  - Subseries 1: University of Chicago Athletic Scrapbooks
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 197, November, 1926 - Includes varsity football, basketball, swimming, new football uniforms, the coaching profession, National Collegiate Athletic Association and the Olympics, criticism of football, and a wedding invitation. (Box 225)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 198, January-march, 1927 - Contains varsity basketball, fencing, track, swimming, wrestling, gymnastics, game and meet schedules, criticism and reform of football, football rules, interscholastic athletics, and the University of Chicago’s all-time football heroes. Also includes wedding invitations, programs and flyers for varsity basketball and Ninth Annual National Interscholastic Basketball Tournament, and an invitation to the Third Annual Intramural Indoor Carnival. (Box 226)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 199, April-June, 1927 - Includes varsity track, golf, tennis, wrestling, swimming, baseball, basketball rules, spring football, Prince Schmeul Khaninia of Abyssinia plays football, interscholastic athletics and tournaments, and wedding invitations. (Box 226)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 200, June, 1927 - Includes varsity golf, tennis, baseball, track, athletic survey of the Big Ten, restrictions on athletic recruitment, features on Paul Stagg, importance of a field house and stadium, Big Ten athletics, coaches, features on A.A Stagg as coach and director at the University of Chicago. (Box 227)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 201, June-October, 1927 - Includes features on how Stagg makes men, standards for enrollment at the University of Chicago, decline of Chicago’s football team, prayer and football, and coaches. (Box 227)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 202, October-November, 1927 - Includes varsity football, players, practices, coaches and games. (Box 228)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 203, November, 1927 - Includes varsity football, yells and cheers, cheerleaders, coaches, and the decline of football at the University of Chicago. (Box 228)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 204, December-January, 1928 - Includes varsity basketball, wrestling, football, swimming, track, the Big Ten, athletic schedules, interscholastic athletics, editorials on campus life and athletics, radio broadcasts, basketball game flyers and a wedding invitation. (Box 229)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 205, January-March, 1928 - Includes varsity track, basketball, swimming, wrestling, fencing, gymnastics, University of Chicago field house, football drills, Olympic contenders, basketball flyers, a letter regarding the history of interscholastic basketball, and a program for the Fourth Annual Intramural Indoor Athletic Carnival. (Box 229)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 206, April-June, 1928 - Includes varsity swimming, track, baseball, tennis, golf, interscholastic athletics, controversy, criticisms and problems with the Amateur Athletics Union and the Olympics, Jack Dempsey, Charles Paddock, Olympic trials, obituaries of former players, gift of a new gymnasium for the University of Chicago, 1933 World’s Fair, flyers for the Chicago-Northwestern Rail Road Line Vacation Bureau, and an invitation the Third Annual Interscholastic Wrestling Tournament. (Box 230)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 207, June-August, 1927 - Includes 1928 Olympics, varsity track, baseball, golf, tennis, football, national games and Olympic trials at Soldier’s Field, Charles Paddock v. Amateur Athletics Union and the Olympic Committee, a wedding invitation, and an invitation to the Twenty-fifth Anniversary of the Order of the “C” banquet. (Box 230)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 208, August-October, 1928 - Includes 1928 Olympics, varsity football, players and coaches, three generations of the Stagg family, basketball rules, and the Blackfeet Indians and football. (Box 231)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 209, October-November, 1928 - Includes varsity football, coaches, players, and a wedding invitation. (Box 231)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 210, November, 1928-January, 1929 - Includes varsity football, wrestling, basketball, track, swimming, decline and corruption within the Amateur Athletics Union, the Tribune Football Trophy, Stagg retires from coaching track, football coaches, rules, and changes in the game, list of all United States sports champions for 1928, and a wedding invitation. (Box 232)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 211, January-April, 1929 - Includes British Sports Champions, 1928, varsity basketball, swimming, wrestling, gymnastics, fencing, track, women’s swimming, National Amateur Athletics Federation v. Amateur Athletics Union, the Big Ten and the Amateur Athletics Union, interscholastic basketball, wedding invitations, basketball flyers, and programs for swimming, the Fifth Annual Intramural Carnival, and the National Interscholastic Basketball Tournament. (Box 232)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 212, April-May, 1929 - Amateur Athletics Union, varsity tennis, track, baseball, golf, colleges subsidizing athletes, University of Iowa expelled from the Includes interscholastic high school basketball and wrestling, Big Ten, and a birth announcement. (Box 233)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 213, May-June, 1929 - Contains varsity tennis, golf, baseball, interscholastic track, colleges proselytizing and subsidizing athletes, and University of Iowa and the Big Ten. (Box 233)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 214, August-October, 1929 - Includes varsity football, Stagg coaching at 67, Robert Maynard Hutchins, decline of athletics at the University of Chicago, football heroes of the past, University of Iowa and the Big Ten, and the need of scholarship over athletics. (Box 234)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 215,October-November, 1929 - Includes varsity football, commercialism and player subsidizing in college athletics, abuses and evils of football, athletic scholarships, coaches, recruiting tactics, Chief Justice W.H Taft on college athletics, Paul Stagg plays for Chicago, and a football program. (Box 234)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 216, November, 1929 - Includes varsity football, players, reunions, decline of the University of Chicago football team, new University field house, Robert Maynard Hutchins to become president at the University of Chicago, War Mothers of America and the founding of Mother’s Day, and a letter about a special train for the Chicago v. Illinois game. (Box 235)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 217, November-December, 1929 - Includes varsity football, basketball, cross-country running, Amateur Athletics Union v. National Collegiate Athletic Association, coverage of Robert M. Hutchins assuming the presidency of the University of Chicago and the welcoming ceremonies, Hutchins’ reforms and teaching methods, University of Iowa and the Big Ten, a wedding invitation, and subsidizing and commercialization of football. (Box 235)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 218, December, 1929-January, 1930 - Includes University of Iowa and the Big Ten, football competition and subsidizing, changes in Olympics rules, professionalism in athletics, varsity football, basketball, wrestling, swimming, gymnastics, track, a wedding invitation and basketball game flyers. (Box 236)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 219, January-March, 1930 - Includes varsity basketball, swimming, wrestling, fencing, gymnastics, 1930 Davis Cup coverage, University of Iowa and the Big Ten, the origins of Mother’s Day, ban on interscholastic tournaments held at universities, Big Ten coaches, basketball flyers, and a program for the Third Annual Wrestling Invitation Tournament Finals. (Box 236)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 220, March-April, 1930 - Includes varsity track, wrestling, tennis, baseball, Big Ten coaches, interscholastic, basketball, Prohibition at American Universities, President Robert M. Hutchins and interscholastic meets, Stagg and the abolishment of interscholastic meets, and obituaries and memorials for Walter Eckersall. (Box 237)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 221, April-June, 1930 - Includes varsity track, golf, baseball, tennis, football coaches, and debates on the abolishment of interscholastic meets. (Box 237)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 222, June-September, 1930 - Includes interscholastic track meets, NCAA track championships, varsity football, tennis, and University of Chicago baseball team to return to Japan, Julius Rosenwald donation for new residence halls at the University of Chicago, football players, coaches, and strategies. (Box 238)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 223, September-November, 1930 - Includes varsity football, University of Chicago baseball team in Japan, Paul Stagg as quarterback, plans for a new university field house, football coaches, Rockefeller family withdraws financial support to the University of Chicago, Olympics Association, and a wedding invitation. (Box 239)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 224, November, 1930-February, 1931 - Covers charity football games, varsity swimming, basketball, track, gymnastics, wrestling, Japan and baseball, President Hutchins and faculty set out education standards of achievement and comprehensive exams for the University of Chicago. Also has athletic schedules, education and improvements at the University of Chicago, interscholastic events, discontinuation of interscholastic basketball and the Big Ten, University of Iowa and the Big Ten, and subsidizing and violations of colleges and athletes. (Box 240)
    - Athletic scrapbook No. 225,March-September, 1931 - This scrapbook covers varsity wrestling, basketball, swimming, track, tennis, football, baseball, golf, fencing, women’s golf, control of the Big Ten, alcohol at the University of Chicago, subsidizing of athletes, University of Iowa and the Big Ten, memorial for Knute Rockne, interscholastic tournaments, university field house, and Olympic trials. (Box 241)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 226, September-November, 1931 - Contains varsity football, new field house, retrospective of Stagg’s career and life, radio broadcasts of games, and Stagg coaches his fortieth year at the University of Chicago. (Box 242)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 227, November, 1931-April, 1932 - Includes varsity football, basketball, swimming, fencing, gymnastics, wrestling, baseball, tennis, golf, track, Big Ten coaches, athletic schedules, player eligibility, University of Chicago field house, President Hutchins’ education reforms, interscholastic Christmas basketball tournament, U.S. tennis tournaments, the construction of the International House at the University of Chicago, and coaching positions and changes. (Box 243)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 228, May-November, 1932 - Includes varsity tennis, track, baseball, golf, football, cross-country running, interscholastic athletics, Olympic trials, Stagg retires as director of the Department of Physical Culture and football coach, and the greatest football moments as told by former University of Chicago stars. (Box 244)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 229, November, 1932-June, 1933 - Stagg’s retirement from the University of Chicago, varsity football, cross-country running, swimming, basketball, wrestling, track, gymnastics, baseball, tennis, and women’s varsity golf. Also contains interscholastic wrestling, discontinuation of interscholastic track events, Big Ten intramurals, Charles D. Shaughnessy to coach at Chicago, Stagg coaching retrospectives, Jesse Owens, Stagg to coach at the College of the Pacific in Stockton, California, and the Rose Bowl. (Box 245)
  - Subseries 2: College of the Pacific Athletic Scrapbooks
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 1, August-November, 1933 - Varsity football at the College of the Pacific, West Coast University football teams and players, football at the University of Chicago, and honors for Coach Stagg. (Box 246)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 2, December, 1933-September, 1934 - Includes football at the College of the Pacific, football schedules, basketball, Chicago Alumni honor Stagg, National Collegiate Athletic Association track championships, use of movie cameras during races and meets, Chicago Bears, and feature articles on the Stagg family. (Box 246)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 3, September-December, 1934 (1 Oversize Folder) - Football at the College of the Pacific, accounts of games and players, veteran coaches, Big Ten football dates, benefit football games, Stella Stagg as football scout, and the early years of football under Stagg. (see Box 338 for oversized items) (Box 247)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 4, January, 1935-April, 1936 - Includes football at the College of the Pacific, athletic schedules, Stagg’s coaching philosophy, track, features and photographs of the Stagg family, spring training, and player profiles. (Box 247)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 5, May, 1936-October, 1937 - This scrapbook contains football at the College of the Pacific, basketball, Far Western Conference teams, Stagg coaching at 74, and player profiles. Also has coverage of the 1937 Sun Bowel in El Paso, Texas, spring training, Central Methodist Church advertisement for “Death takes the steering wheel: booze and gasoline don’t mix,” and advertisement about Stagg as a football coach. (Box 248)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 6, October, 1937-November, 1937 - Includes football at the College of the Pacific, Far Western Conference teams, giants in football (including Stagg, Knute Rockne, Walter Camp, Walter Eckersall, Red Grange, and Jim Thorpe), and Stagg returns to the University of Chicago, interviews with Stagg. Also includes articles on Stella Stagg as football scout, University of Chicago football vs. College of the Pacific, and ceremonies at the University of Chicago honoring Stagg. (Box 248)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 7, November, 1938-October, 1939 - University of Chicago football team vs. College of the Pacific, professionalism in athletics, President Robert M. Hutchins on athletics, articles on the Stagg family, electronic scoreboards, honors and tributes to Stagg, College of the Pacific athletic field, and a report on the College of the Pacific athletics. Also contains train schedules and itineraries, programs, and a handwritten football notice by Stagg to his players. (Box 249)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 8, October, 1939-November, 1940 - Includes College of the Pacific football, Stagg coaches fiftieth season, football in Hawaii, features on Stella Stagg, establishment of the Amos Alonzo Stagg Memorial Award, football coaches, University of Chicago drops football, intramural football at the University of Chicago, and College of the Pacific newsletters and alumni announcements. (Box 249)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 9, November, 1940-September, 1942 (1 Oversize Folder) - College of the Pacific football, West Coast conference football teams, features on players and coaches in the West, University of Chicago football, Stagg receives awards, honors and tributes, and Stagg’s career highlights and retrospectives. Also contains football bowl games, articles on the Stagg family, the impact of World War II on College of the Pacific and intercollegiate football in America, and section of the Chicago Tribune, Sunday, September 14, 1941 on University of Chicago and Presidents William Rainey Harper and Robert Maynard Hutchins (oversize) (see Box 338 for oversized items). (Box 250)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 10, September, 1942-October, 1943 - Football at the College of the Pacific, the impact of World War II on players and football, articles on Stella Stagg, causality lists of College of the Pacific alumni, Army ban on football, military training at the College of the Pacific, and tributes to Stagg. Also contains a comic strip featuring Stagg, telegrams, and a games statistics chart for the College of the Pacific vs. UCLA football game. (Box 250)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 11, October, 1943-January, 1944 (1 Oversize Folder) - Includes College of the Pacific football, bowl tournaments, Stagg’s career highlights, awards, the importance and significance of football during the war, articles with Stella Stagg, American Magazine feature on the an air battle against the Luftwaffe, and a Pacific Weekly, from November 26, 1943 (oversize). (see Box 338 for oversized items) (Box 251)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 12, February, 1944-September, 1946 - Contains the impact of World War II on football, Chicago drops athletics during the War, Iwo Jima, College of the Pacific football, articles on the Stagg family, football radio broadcasts, and honors for Stagg. (Box 251)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 13, September, 1946-December, 1946 (1 Oversize Folder) - College of the Pacific football, enrollment at the College of the Pacific and Stockton Junior College, Stagg’s contributions to football, deterioration and disuse of Stagg field at the University of Chicago, the Stagg family, Stagg coaches at Susquehanna University, and pamphlet for the College of the Pacific Building Program (oversize). (see Box 338 for oversized) (Box 252)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 14, 1952-1954 - Includes articles on Stagg in his nineties, receptions and honors for Stagg, and coaching football. (Box 252)
  - Subseries 3: Amos Alonzo Stagg Career and Personal Scrapbooks
    - Career Scrapbook No. 1, 1886-1924 - Includes articles on Stagg as pitcher for Yale University, religion and students at Yale, 1888 football season for Yale, Benjamin Harrison and Levi Morton elected President and Vice President of the United States, and Walter Camp, Springfield College YMCA football, and features on Stagg’s lectures on modern athletics. Also contains the opening of the University of Chicago, President William Rainey Harper, the development of football at the University of Chicago, Stagg on sports and the modern athlete, John D. Rockefeller, the first Convocation at Chicago, and development and rules for baseball and football at the University of Chicago. Incorporated into the scrapbook are Yale memorabilia (including a math exam, the Yale News financial report, reception programs, college and glee club songs, and a handwritten schedule of 1888 Yale baseball games), cartoons and profiles on players. (Box 253)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 2, January, 1925- January, 1928 - Articles on Stagg’s career, editorials, coverage of Stagg’s lecture tours and addresses, promotion of athletics in education, fundraising campaign for University of Chicago athletics, and football at the University of Chicago. Also contains articles on the Stagg family, debate over Prohibition and the Anti Saloon League, Stagg’s involvement and endorsement of Prohibition and the Volstead Act, amateurism, Stagg publishes Touchdown, famous football coaches, funeral of President Judson, university intramurals and interscholastic athletics, and the growth of football. The scrapbook also has Chicago Alumni club invitations and flyers, City Club of Chicago 1925 Fall Announcements, letters, and programs for the Hyde Park Baptist Union Sunday services. (Box 254)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 3, January, 1928-February, 1930 - Coverage of Stagg’s speaking engagements and lecture tours, the value of athletics and clean living, Stagg’s advice to youth, coaches and alumni relations, coaching football, athletics builds character, amateurism, brief biographies and career highlights of Stagg, the Stagg family, and football at the University of Chicago. Also contains letters, programs for dedications, banquets and ceremonies, and a note with a bill payment for a local equipment supplier. (Box 255)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 4, March, 1930-September, 1931 - Includes articles on Stagg’s advice for good living, the debate over Prohibition and the Eighteenth Amendment, Stagg’s testimony before the House Judiciary Committee, Prohibition hearings, the death of Walter Eckersall, athletic problems at the University of Chicago, and the Stagg family. Also contains letters, and handwritten notes and schedules for athletics at the University of Chicago. (Box 256)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 5, October 12, 1931-October 7, 1932 - Retrospectives and highlights of Stagg’s coaching career at the University of Chicago, articles on “how to be a good [football] player, changes in football since 1892, Big Ten picks for 1931 season and debates over Prohibition. Also contains Stagg’s contributions to football, brief biography on Stagg, articles on football coaches, letters, song sheets, and a fraternity membership certificate. (Box 257)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 6, October-December, 1932 - Includes football at the University of Chicago, Stagg’s resignation and career highlights, a biographical sketch, Chicago players greatest moments in football, tributes to Stagg, articles on coaches and coaching, and letters to Stagg. (Box 258)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 7, December, 1932-January, 1934 - Coverage on Stagg’s career, lecture tours, amateurism, Stagg leaving Chicago and heading to the College of the Pacific, honors, awards, tributes, articles on the Stagg family, football rules, a flyer from the Chicago Alumni Association, and letters to Stagg from Prohibition Organizations. (Box 259)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 8, February, 1934-July, 1935 - Includes 1920’s sports articles, Stagg’s honors, tributes and career highlights, and coverage of lecture tours. Also contains College of the Pacific track and football, the Stagg sons, history of the curve ball, Stella R. Stagg, former Chicago stars and their careers, the benefits of athletics, polls on all-star football coaches, letters, telegrams, and brochures. (Box 260)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 9, August, 1935-February, 1938 - Contains articles on the Stagg family, football at the College of the Pacific, obituaries of players, benefits of temperance, tributes, honors and banquets for Stagg and his contributions and innovations to coaching and football. Also contains membership certificates, letters, telegrams, flyers, and a program for the Silver Buffalo award. (Box 261)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 10, February, 1938-June, 1939 - College of the Pacific football vs. University of Chicago, articles about “clean living,” honors and tributes to Stagg, the decline of University of Chicago football, “Gate Receipts and Glory,” by Robert M. Hutchins, problems with athletics at American collegiate institutions. Also contains University of Chicago football brochures and tickets, menus, College of the Pacific Alumni News Special, newsletters, and invitations. (Box 262)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 11, August, 1939-March, 1940 - Includes celebration of fifty years of Stagg’s coaching, football at the College of the Pacific, a transcript of Bill Stern’s October 8, 1939 broadcast and profile of A.A. Stagg, University of Chicago abolishes football, Stagg career retrospectives, subsidizing of athletes, honors and awards. Also contains a receipt with pen studies by Charles Paxton Zaner, letters, ticket order forms, and poems. (Box 262)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 12, April, 1940-December, 1941 - Covers the University of Chicago ban on football, College of the Pacific land grant, tributes, career highlights, awards, Stagg’s influence on intercollegiate athletics, Knute Rockne movie, the Stagg family, biographical sketches (including degrees, organizations and published works), and Stagg’s importance and impact as a trainer of young men. (Box 263)
    - Career Scrapbook No. 13, January, 1942-December, 1943 - The state of athletics at the University of Chicago, influence of World War II on intercollegiate football, articles on the Stagg family (including Stella R. Stagg, Paul Stagg, Ruth Stagg Lauren and children), tributes and honors for Stagg, brief biographies and awards. (Box 263)